<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Digital Cat - pelican</title><link href="https://www.thedigitalcatonline.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.thedigitalcatonline.com/categories/pelican/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.thedigitalcatonline.com/</id><updated>2019-06-07T15:30:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Adventures of a curious cat in the land of programming</subtitle><entry><title>Run a blog with pelican</title><link href="https://www.thedigitalcatonline.com/blog/2019/06/07/run-a-pelican-blog/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-07T15:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-07T15:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Leonardo Giordani</name></author><id>tag:www.thedigitalcatonline.com,2019-06-07:/blog/2019/06/07/run-a-pelican-blog/</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest piece of advice I can give to beginner developers is: write a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing, and in general teaching, is a perfect way to understand concepts. Some say that you cannot claim you understood something until you can explain it properly. This unfortunately doesn't take into account that not everyone is a good communicator, and writing (also technical writing) is an art, not just a set of checkboxes to tick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, explaining a concept forces you to try to organise your thought, to write them down in a sequential way, to explore corners that you take for granted while the concepts involved are all but simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my advice is once again: write a blog. Share your experience as a programmer, mathematician, physicist, data scientist (and thousands of other interesting jobs that I can't mention here). Don't worry if you don't have a revolutionary discovery to share with others. We are standing on the shoulders of giants, and every little contribution is welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my most successful posts on this blog is something I wrote after fighting for 3 hours with a trivial Python syntax mistake. I was already a senior programmer, I did a novice mistake. I shared the solution and now that post has a huge amount of visits every day, which hopefully means that some people stuck with the same problem can quickly find a solution. Maybe these people will one day write the new Google or the new AWS, and I'm glad I helped them today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="pelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#pelican" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I run this blog since 2013. I wanted to use a static website generator because I liked the simplicity of the concept, and since GitHub was providing free hosting on &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; I considered it a viable option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with &lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a very well-known static website generator written in Ruby, because it was the system used by the vast majority of technical bloggers out there at the time. Unfortunately I'm not a Ruby programmer, so every issue I had with the build system that ended in a crash was a mystery to me. I also wanted to add functionalities to the system, and the language once again was a barrier. Jekyll is surely a very good system but it didn't suit my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I didn't have the time to study Ruby at that point, I tried to find a good static site generator written in Python, a language that I know, and I found it in &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. Arguably, the Pelican website is not graphically amazing, and this worried me a bit, but I quickly discovered that the whole system is pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 6 years, with the help of Pelican, I developed a wonderfully simple blogging work flow based on Git, so I decided to share my Pelican setup with a Cookiecutter template. Recently I refurbished the template to update it with the latest changes that I made to my personal setup and I realised that, despite the documentation, setting up a blog based on pelican might still be difficult for some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will show you how to create your blog from scratch using Pelican. You don't need to know Python to use it, even though, as it happened to me with Jekyll, it might help if you want to get involved in the development of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also run Pelican without this template, just follow the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/install.html"&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt; on the official documentation. My template simplifies the initial installation, and creates some script that make you follow a specific work flow, but you are free to change them to suit you needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not acquainted with static web sites have a look at the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Static_web_page"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="prerequisites"&gt;Prerequisites&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#prerequisites" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to have &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/"&gt;Python 3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; installed in your system. &lt;a href="https://github.com/petervanderdoes/gitflow-avh"&gt;Git Flow&lt;/a&gt; is optional, so if you don't want to use it you can avoid installing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="github"&gt;GitHub&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#github" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to create two repositories in your GitHub account. The first one will host the source files of your blog (the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; repository), while the second one will host the actual static site files (deploy repository). Follow the instructions &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/articles/create-a-repo"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you are not sure how to create them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call the first repository &lt;code&gt;blog_source&lt;/code&gt; and the second one &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;your_user_name&amp;gt;.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. The former is just a convention followed by my template, while the latter is enforced by GitHub pages, which uses by default that repository to publish the website at the address with that name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="install-the-template"&gt;Install the template&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#install-the-template" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/tutorial/venv.html"&gt;Python virtual environment&lt;/a&gt; and install &lt;code&gt;cookiecutter&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pip install cookiecutter
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then run &lt;code&gt;cookiecutter&lt;/code&gt; on the template I prepared&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;cookiecutter https://github.com/lgiordani/cookiecutter-pelicanblog.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, you will be asked some questions, let's look at them in detail. Remember that you can always start from scratch of fix the values you entered manually later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;github_username [yourusername]&lt;/code&gt; - Well, this should be self-explanatory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;blog_source_repo [blog_source]&lt;/code&gt; - This is just the name of the source repository that you created on GitHub. You can accept the default if you didn't change the name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;deploy_repository [yourusername.github.com]&lt;/code&gt; - This is the name of the deploy repository, i.e. the one that contains the actual static website. The default value is already filled with your GitHub username, so if you are setting up a GitHub Pages blog you can just accept it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;deploy_directory [deploy]&lt;/code&gt; - The local directory where the deploy repository is cloned and that will be updated by the deployment process. By default, this is set to &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; inside the project directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;use_versioning [y]&lt;/code&gt; - Say &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; if you want to have a release process for your website with a version number and associated Git tags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;use_git_flow [y]&lt;/code&gt; - Say &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; if you want to initialise Git Flow on the repository (you need to have Git Flow already installed in the system).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="set-up-the-environment"&gt;Set up the environment&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#set-up-the-environment" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now enter the directory that was created by the template, install the requirements and run the &lt;code&gt;setup.sh&lt;/code&gt; script&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; &amp;lt;blog_source_repo&amp;gt;
pip install -r requirements.txt
./setup.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This script performs the following actions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it initializes git in the local repository, adding the source repository as a remote with the name &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you decided to use Git Flow, it initializes the repository, creating the &lt;code&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt; branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it clones the https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-plugins repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it clones the https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-themes repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it creates the &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; directory which is a local clone one of the deploy repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="configure-pelican"&gt;Configure Pelican&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#configure-pelican" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now everything is ready to run the &lt;code&gt;pelican-quickstart&lt;/code&gt; script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pelican-quickstart
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This script asks the following questions. I marked with a &lt;strong&gt;!!!&lt;/strong&gt; the answers that are not up to you but depend on the current setup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Where do you want to create your new web site? [.]&lt;/code&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;!!!&lt;/strong&gt; Answer &lt;code&gt;pelican&lt;/code&gt; so everything will be installed in that directory inside the current one, keeping the installation tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;What will be the title of this web site?&lt;/code&gt; - This is up to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Who will be the author of this web site?&lt;/code&gt; - This is up to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;What will be the default language of this web site? [en]&lt;/code&gt; - This is up to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Do you want to specify a URL prefix? e.g., https://example.com   (Y/n)&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;!!!&lt;/strong&gt; Answer &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;What is your URL prefix? (see above example; no trailing slash)&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;!!!&lt;/strong&gt; This is &lt;code&gt;https://&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.github.io&lt;/code&gt; if you are using GH pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Do you want to enable article pagination? (Y/n)&lt;/code&gt; - This is up to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;How many articles per page do you want? [10]&lt;/code&gt; - This is up to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;What is your time zone? [Europe/Paris]&lt;/code&gt; - This is up to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Do you want to generate a tasks.py/Makefile to automate generation and publishing? (Y/n)&lt;/code&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;!!!&lt;/strong&gt; Answer &lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; to all the following questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions on this part you can read the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/install.html"&gt;Pelican documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can enter the &lt;code&gt;pelican&lt;/code&gt; directory and run &lt;code&gt;make devserver&lt;/code&gt; which will run the development server at http://localhost:8000. &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/publish.html#make"&gt;This page&lt;/a&gt; of the official documentation explains all the options of the Makefile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-work-flow"&gt;The work flow&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#the-work-flow" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work flow that you will follow using this setup is the following (I assume you use Git Flow, change the git commands accordingly if you are using another flow)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a git branch: &lt;code&gt;git flow feature start &amp;lt;branch&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create one or more new articles / Edit previous articles: create the files as &lt;code&gt;pelican/content/&amp;lt;slug&amp;gt;.markdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commit: &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt; (repeat 2 and 3 until you are satisfied with the results)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merge the branch: &lt;code&gt;git flow feature finish&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release: &lt;code&gt;./release.sh&lt;/code&gt; (this runs Punch to create a new release)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy: &lt;code&gt;./deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; (this runs Pelican to create the static site and copies everything in the &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; directory)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish: &lt;code&gt;./publish.sh&lt;/code&gt; (this adds, commits, and pushes the files in the &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; directory)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each one of these steps, with the notable exception of the second one, is performed through a single command and takes up to few seconds in the worst case. I prefer to have control on the publishing process, so often I run the git commands manually in the &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; directory, but you can safely use the provided Make directive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="versioning"&gt;Versioning&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#versioning" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Versioning is not the most important thing to do in a blog, but I personally like to have a trace of what I created and when in my Git log. I use &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/punch.py/"&gt;Punch&lt;/a&gt;, a package that I developed to replace bumpversion. If you want to customise the default versioning scheme contained in the template read the &lt;a href="https://punch.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;Punch documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Python3"></category><category term="pelican"></category></entry></feed>